Guide to the Eveline Mabel Burns Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Eveline Mabel Burns Papers
[ca. 1930]-1985.
Burns, Eveline Mabel Richardson, 1900-1985
41.5 linear ft (ca. 50,000 items in 99 boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
MS#0171
4078565
This collection contains correspondence, manuscripts, notes, documents, student files and printed material relating to social worker, Eveline Mabel Richardson Burns, [ca. 1930]-1985.
Biographical Note
Eveline Mabel Richardson Burns (1900-1985) was Professor of Social Work, New York School of Social Work, 1946-1967.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts of books, articles, book reviews and speeches, course materials, students' files, file reflecting a broad range of activities in the field of social welfare such as Social Security, unemployment, health care, and social work education. Also, an extensive file of printed materials.
Arrangement
Selected materials cataloged; remainder arranged. This collection is arranged in four series:
Series I: Catalogued Correspondence
Series II: Correspondence, Manuscripts and Related Material
Series III: Subject File
Series IV: Printed Material, Student Files and Miscellaneous
Subjects
Columbia University.--School of Social Work--Faculty.; Social work education.; Public welfare.; Unemployment insurance.; Social security.; Reviews.; Speeches.; Economists.; Women college teachers.
Acquisition
1970 M-70 New York School of Social Work Transfer
Transferred from the New York School of Social Work, 1970 & 1978; transferred from the Columbia University Department of Economics, 1987.
Access Restrictions
The following boxes are located off-site: Boxes 1-99. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
- Series I: Catalogued Correspondence
  - Angell, James R. (Box A)
  - Angell, James W. (Box A)
  - Barzun, Jacques (Box A)
  - Bernays, Edward L. (Box A)
  - Bradley, Omar Nelson (Box A)
  - Bunche, Ralph Johnson (Box A)
  - Caine, Sir Sydney (Box A)
  - Canfield, Cass (Box A)
  - Cornmager, Henry Steele (Box A)
  - Douglas, Paul Howard (Box A)
  - Dulles, Eleanor Lansing (Box A)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight David (Box A)
  - Folks, Homer (Box A)
  - Friedman, Milton (Box A)
  - Galbraith, John Kenneth (Box A)
  - Garrett, Garet (Box A)
  - Gardner, John William (Box A)
  - Gifford, John Sherman (Box A)
  - Goldberg, Arthur Joseph (Box A)
  - Hanks, Nancy (Box A)
  - Harriman, William Averell (Box A)
  - Javits, Jacob Koppel (Box A)
  - Kennedy, Robert Francis (Box A)
  - Lenroot, Katharine Fredrica (Box A)
  - Lindsay, John Vliet (Box A)
  - Meyer, Agnes Ernst (Mrs Eugene) (Box A)
  - Myrdal, Alva Reimer (Mrs Gunnar) (Box A)
  - Myrdal, Gunnar Karl (Box A)
  - Pearson, Lester Bowles (Box A)
  - Reuther, Walter Philip (Box A)
  - Rockefeller, Nelson Aldrich (Box A)
  - Roosevelt, Eleanor Roosevelt (Box A)
  - Rusk, Dean (Box A)
  - Samuelson, Paul Anthony (Box A)
  - Smathers, George A. (Box A)
  - Sparkman, John (Box A)
  - Stevenson, Adlai Ewing (Box A)
  - Sulzberger, Arthur Hays (Box A)
  - Taussig, Frank William (Box A)
  - Van Doren, Carl Clinton (Box A)
  - Wilkins, Roy (Box A)
  - Wirtz, William Willard (Box A)
  - Wootton of Abinger, Barbara Frances Adam Wootton, Baroness (Box A)
  - Young, Whitney Moore, Jr. (Box A)
- Series II: Correnspondence, Manuscripts and Related Material
  - Correspondence (Box 1-5)
    - Chronological, 1939-1970
      - 1939-1948 (Box 1)
      - 1949-1952 (Box 2)
      - 1953-1961 (Box 3)
      - 1961-1965 (Box 4)
      - 1965-1970 (Box 5)
    - Topics--A - Z (Box 6)
  - Manuscripts and Related Material, 1948-1964 (Box 7-10)
    - Miscellaneous Manuscripts (Box 11)
    - Printed Material by E. M. Burns (Box 11)
    - Cards for Index to The American Social Security System by E. M. Burns (Box 11)
- Series III: Subject File
  - Aid to Dependent Children (Box 11)
  - Aid to Families with Dependent Children (Box 11)
  - Alabama Unemployment Commission (Box 11)
  - American Assembly (Box 12)
  - American Association of Schools of Social Work (Box 12)
  - American Association of Social Workers (Box 13)
  - American Association of University Professors, 1958-1960 (Box 13)
  - American Association of University Professors, 1961-1968 (Box 14)
  - American Association of University Women, 1949-1952 (Box 15)
  - American Economic Association, 1945-1948 (Box 15)
  - A. E. A., 1950-1957 (Box 16)
  - American Federation of Labor (Box 16)
  - American Jewish Tercentenary (Box 16)
  - American Public Welfare Association
    - 1951-1952 (Box 16)
    - 1952-1960 (Box 17)
    - 1961-1964 (Box 18)
    - 1961-1962 (Box 95)
  - American Sociological Society (Box 18)
  - Arden House Conference, 1957-1958 (Box 18)
  - Area Redevelopment Administration, 1961-1964 (Box 95)
  - Bell, Winifred (Box 18)
  - Birnberg Study - re: British Health Service (Box 18)
  - British Social Security (Box 18)
  - Brookings Institution (Box 18)
  - Bureau of the Budget (Box 18)
  - E. M. Burns - Personal File (Box 19)
    - Appointments (Box 19)
    - Calendar of Dates (Box 19)
    - Documents Ordered or Requested (Box 19)
    - Personal Folder (Box 19)
    - Engagements
      - Fulfilled, 1948-1960 (Box 19)
      - Refused, 1949-1960 (Box 20)
      - Schedule (Box 20)
    - Papers, Publicity, Etc. (Box 20)
  - California Institute of Industrial Relations, 1961 (Box 20)
  - Canada (Box 96)
  - Canadian Labour Congress, 1965 (Box 20)
  - Child Labor (Box 20)
  - Citizens' Committee for Children, 1964-1965 (Box 20)
  - C. C. C., 1967-1969 (Box 21)
  - Citizens Union (Box 21)
  - Columbia University (Box 21-22)
  - Commerce, Dept. of (Box 22)
  - Commission on the Delivery of Personal Health Services, 1967 (Box 22)
  - Commission on the Status of Women, 1962-1963 (Box 22)
  - Committee on Social Insurance and Taxes, 1962 (Box 22)
  - Community Council of New York, 1964-1965 (Box 22)
  - Comparative Economic Organization (Box 22)
  - Conference on Financing Health Care - Aged, 1956 (Box 23)
  - Congressional Joint Committee on the Economic Report, 1955 (Box 23)
  - Consumers League of America, 1948-1950 (Box 23)
  - C. L. A., 1948-1950 (Box 24)
  - Consumers League of New York, 1948-1951 (Box 24)
  - Council on Social Work Education, 1952-1963 (Box 25)
  - Denmark - Social Security (Box 25)
  - Desmond Hearings - 1949 (Box 25)
  - Disability Insurance (Box 25)
  - Economic Development Administration, 1966 (Box 26)
  - Eleanor Roosevelt Memorial Foundation (Box 26)
  - Family Life Conference, 1957 (Box 26)
  - Family Service Association of America, 1948-1964 (Box 26)
  - Federal Advisory Council
    - 1949-1951 (Box 26)
    - 1952-1957 (Box 27)
    - 1958-1968 (Box 28)
    - 1951-1965 (Box 96-97)
  - Federal Security Agency (Box 29)
    - 1950 - H.R. 6000 (Box 29)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 29)
  - Ford Foundation - Problems re Older Citizens (Box 30)
  - Fox, Martin J. ,1961 (Box 30)
  - Fraser, Hazel (Box 30)
  - Gerontology (Box 30)
  - Guggenheim Application Material (Box 30)
  - Harriman Lecture, 1961-1962 (Box 30)
  - Hathaway Memorial Committee, 1956 (Box 30)
  - Health and Welfare Council, Inc. (Box 30)
  - Health, Education and Welfare, Dept. of
    - 1956-1963 (Box 30)
    - 1963-1967 (Box 31)
    - 1964-1967 (Box 32)
    - 1964-1969 (Box 33)
    - 1966-1968 (Box 34)
  - Health Insurance Plan, N. Y. (Box 34)
  - Health Program, U. S. (Box 34)
  - Health Services Research Project, 1965 (Box 34)
  - Hobby Consultants Group, 1953 (Box 34)
  - Housing Conference - Chicago, 1960 (Box 34)
  - Illinois Are Redevelopment Administration (Box 34)
  - Industrial and Labor Relations (Box 34)
  - Industrial Relations Research Association, 1959-1969 (Box 34)
  - Institutes, Committee on, 1946-1947 (Box 34)
  - Institute for Religous and Social Studies (Box 34)
  - International Conference of Social Work, 1956, 1960-1962 (Box 34)
  - Italian Social Insurance Article (Box 34)
  - King - Anderson Bill, 1964 (Box 34)
  - Labor Department (Box 98)
  - Lasker Lectures, 1952, 1953, 1960 (Box 35)
  - League of Women Voters, 1937 (Box 36)
  - Lenox Hill Neighborhood Association, 1962 (Box 36)
  - London School of Economics, 1963 (Box 36)
  - McConnell - Ford Proposals (Box 36)
  - Maine Welfare Association (Box 36)
  - Marshall Plan (Box 36)
  - Mayo, Leonard (Box 36)
  - Means Test Conference (Box 36)
  - Michigan State University (Box 36)
  - Milk - Orange Juice (Box 36)
  - Minnesota, University of (Box 36)
  - National Advisory Commission on Health Manpower (Box 36)
  - National Association of Social Workers, 1959-1963 (Box 36)
  - National Bureau of Economic Research, 1967-1968 (Box 36)
  - National Conference on Public Health Training, 1967 (Box 37)
  - National Conference on Social Work/Welfare - Name changed in 1956.
    - 1951-1956 (Box 37)
    - 1956-1958 (Box 38)
    - 1958-1959 (Box 39)
    - 1959-1966 (Box 40)
    - 1949-1958 (Box 41)
  - National Council on the Aging, 1965 (Box 42)
  - National Council on Social Work Education, 1948-1951 (Box 42)
  - National Public Advisory Committee, 1961-1966 (Box 42)
    - 1966-1968 (Box 43)
  - National Social Welfare Assembly, 1949-1954, 1959-1963 (Box 43)
  - National Urban League, 1968 (Box 43)
  - New Hampshire (Box 43)
  - New Jersey (Box 43)
  - New York Academy of Medicine, 1965, 1969 (Box 44)
  - New York School of Social Work, 1946-1967 (Box 44)
    - Ad Hoc Committee (Box 44)
    - Administration Committee (Box 44)
    - Advanced Programs (Box 44)
    - Advanced Programs (Box 45)
    - Advisory Committee of the Faculties (Box 45)
    - Alumni Association (Box 45)
    - Board - Faculty Committee (Box 45)
    - Burns, E. M. - Memos, Correspondence (Box 45)
    - Bush's Seminar for the Faculty (Box 45)
    - Curriculum Committee (Box 45)
    - Curriculum Committee (Box 46)
    - Curriculum in Social Policy (Box 46)
    - Curriculum Study Project (Box 46)
    - Development (Box 46)
    - Doctoral Program History (Box 46)
    - Educational Policy (Box 46)
    - Executive Committee (Box 46)
    - Faculty Council (Box 46)
    - Faculty - Student Committee (Box 46)
    - Government and Social Welfare (Box 47)
    - Grading (Box 47)
    - Library Committee (Box 47)
    - Papers (Box 47)
    - Personnel Practices Committee (Box 47)
    - Project Requirement (Box 47)
    - Public Relations and Development Office (Box 47)
    - Publications Committee (Box 47)
    - Replacement Committee (Box 47)
    - Research Area Committee (Box 47)
    - Research Center (Box 48)
    - Salary Adjustment (Box 48)
    - School Council (Box 48)
    - School Organization (Box 48)
    - Social Service Area (Box 48)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 48)
  - New York State Department of Social Welfare (Box 49)
  - New York University (Box 49)
  - North Carolina Conference of Social Work, 1956 (Box 49)
  - Ohio State University, 1964 (Box 50)
  - Ohio Welfare Conference, 1957 (Box 50)
  - Old Age Survivors Insurance (Box 50)
  - Peace Corps Training Program for India, 1966 (Box 50)
  - Pennsylvania, University of (Box 50)
  - Pittsburgh, University of (Box 50)
  - Policy Advisory Committee, 1966 (Box 50)
  - Poor Peoples Campaign (Box 50)
  - President's Commission on the Status of Women, 1962-1963 (Box 50)
  - Princeton Lectures, 1951 (Box 50)
  - Public Administration (Box 50)
  - Public Assistance (Box 50)
  - Public - Private (Box 50)
  - Public Welfare (Box 98)
  - Puerto Rico (Box 50)
  - Regional Advisory Group (Box 51)
  - Rein, Martin (Box 51)
  - The Role of Government in Health. Services (Box 51)
  - Saint Bonaventure University (Box 51)
  - The Seeing Eye - Study of the Blind (Box 51)
  - Shaw Lectures (Box 51)
  - Smith College, 1946, 1960 (Box 51)
  - Social Insurance Terminology (Box 51)
  - Social Security Administration
    - 1946-1947, 1960-1965 (Box 52)
    - 1967-1969 (Box 53)
  - Social Security Appropriations (Box 53)
  - Social Security Board, 1937-1938 (Box 53)
  - Social Security in America (Box 53)
  - Social Security - Miscellaneous (Box 53)
  - Social Welfare - Miscellaneous (Box 53)
  - Social Work Research Group (Box 54)
  - Social Work - Miscellaneous (Box 54)
  - State Department
    - 1962-1963 (Box 54)
    - 1963-1966 (Box 55)
  - Task Force on Income Maintenance (Box 55)
  - Toronto Research Conference, 1953-1954 (Box 55)
  - Toronto Round Table on Social Security, 1948 (Box 55)
  - Training Institute - Mobilization for Youth, Inc., 1964 (Box 55)
  - Treasury Department, 1964 (Box 55)
  - Twentieth Century Fund, 1950-1954 (Box 56)
  - Unemployment Committee (Box 56)
  - Unemployment Insurance (Box 56)
  - Unemployment--Miscellaneous (Box 98)
  - United Automobile Workers of America (Box 56)
  - United Auto Workers Social Security Committee, 1949 (Box 98)
  - United Nations
    - Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization, 1957 (Box 56)
    - Seminar on Social Welfare, 1955 (Box 56)
    - Study on Social Services, 1964 (Box 56)
  - U. C. L. A., 1965 (Box 57)
  - Upjohn Institute, 1968-1969 (Box 57)
  - Veterans - Research Project (Box 57)
  - Weld, W. E. (Box 57)
  - Welfare Administration, 1965 (Box 57)
  - Welfare and Health Council, NYC, 1948-1956 (Box 98-99)
  - Welfare State (Box 57)
  - Western College for Women, 1962 (Box 57)
  - Western Michigan University, 1968 (Box 57)
  - Western Reserve University, 1962, 1963, 1966 (Box 57)
  - White House Conference on Aging (Box 57)
  - White House Conference on Children and Youth (Box 57)
  - Withers Report on Relief Financing, 1937 (Box 57)
  - Women's City Club
    - 1948-1949 (Box 99)
    - 1950-1952 (Box 57)
  - Miscellaneous Loose Materials (Box 57)
- Series IV: Printed Material, Student Files and Miscellaneous
  - Course Materials and Student Files (Box 58-63)
  - Student Papers (Box 64)
  - Miscellaneous Notes (Box 65)
  - Memorabilia (Box 65)
  - Printed Material (Box 65)
  - Printed Materials, including Mimeographs (Box 66-87)
  - Printed Materials with Correspondence or Notes Attached (Box 88)
  - Printed Materials - Agendas and Materials for Conferences (Box 89)
  - Printed Materials by E. M. Burns (Box 90-92)
    - 1930 - 59 (Box 90)
    - 1960 - 61 (Box 91)
    - 1962 - 69 (Box 92)
  - Manuscripts and Typescripts by E. M. Burns (Box 93)
  - Publicity and Reviews of Books by E. M. Burns (Box 93)
  - Miscellaneous Typescripts (Box 93)
  - Memoranda and Typed Papers (Box 93)
  - Galley Proofs (Box 93)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence (Not with E. M. Burns) (Box 94)
  - Notes (Box 94)
  - Clippings (Box 94)